本章我们看出现在模运算中的
In this module, we're going to look at some hard problems
一些难题
that come up in the context of modular arithmetic.
这些难题将是我们下周构建的密码系统的基础
These problems are going to be the basis of the cryptosystems that we build next week.
首先我想说，模运算中也有很多简单的问题
So first I'd like to mention that there are many easy problems in modular arithmetic.
比如说，如果你给我一个整数N，给我一个Z_N中的指数x
For example, if you give me an integer N, and you give me an  element x in ZN,
使用欧几里得算法找到x的逆是很容易的
finding the inverse of x is actually very easy using the Euclidean algorithm.
类似地，如果你给我一个质数p，给我某个多项式f
Similarly, if you give me a prime p, and you give me some polynomial f,
找到Z_p中的一个元素，使得它是这个多项式的根也很容易
then finding an element in Zp that's a root of this polynomial is also relatively easy,
事实上有一个有效的算法，用时与多项式次数成线性
and in fact there's an efficient algorithm that can do it in linear time in the degree of the polynomial.
至少对于低次数的多项式，找到这些方程的质数模的根
So at least for low-degree polynomials, finding roots of these polynomials modulo primes
是很容易
is actually quite easy.
(根据Galois理论，5次以上多项式方程无一般代数解)
但是模算法的很多问题是很难的
However many problems in modular arithmetic are actually quite difficult,
如我所说，这些困难的问题组成了许多公钥密码系统的基础
and as I said, these difficult, these difficult problems form the basis of many public-key cryptosystems.
那么我们来看一些经典的质数模的困难问题
So let's look at some classic hard problems modulo primes.
那么固定某个大质数p，比如p是某个600位的质数
So fix some large prime p, so think of p as some 600-digit prime,
我们固定Z_p^*中的某个元素g
and let's fix some element g in Zp*
我们假设这个元素g的阶正好是数q
And let's assume that the order of this element g happens to be a number q.
现在，考虑一个指数函数，将x映射到g^x
Now, consider the exponentiation function that simply maps a number x to the element g^x.
上一节我们证明了这个函数是容易计算的
We showed in the last segment that this function is easy to compute
使用重复平方算法，那么事实上计算g^x可以非常有效
using the repeated squaring algorithm, so in fact computing g^x can be done quite efficiently,
但现在我们看相反的问题
but now let's look at the inverse question.
相反的问题是，给定g^x，我想找出它的对数
So the inverse problem is basically, given g^x, now I want you to find its logarithm,
即值x。如我所说，在实数上，给定g^x
namely the value x. As I said, over the reals, over the real numbers, given g to the x, find x is exactly the definition of
找x就是对数函数的定义，但这里我让大家去找质数模p下的对数
the logarithm function, but here I ask you to find the logarithm modulo a prime p.
那么这个问题叫做离散对数问题，Dlog
So this problem is called the discrete logarithm problem, Dlog,
我说，g^x的以g为底的离散对数是这个指数x
and I'll say that the discrete logarithm of g to the x base g is basically the exponent x.
那么g^x的离散对数是x，我们的目标是输出指数x，
x在0到q-2的范围里
So the discrete logarithm of g to the x is x, so our goal is to output some exponent x in 0 to q-2
正好是log_g x
that happens to be the logarithm of g to the x.
那么我们来看一个例子。假设我们看整数模11
So let's look at an example. Suppose we look at the integers modulo 11,
这里我们写下Z_11里的离散对数函数，底数为2
and here I wrote down the discrete log function in Z11, base 2.
我们看这个函数如何工作
So let's look at how this function behaves.
首先，1的离散对数是0，因为2的0次方是1
So first of all, the discrete logarithm of 1 is 0, because 2 to the 0 is equal to 1.
类似地，2的离散对数是1，因为2的1次方是2
Similarly the discrete logarithm of 2 is 1, because 2 to the 1 is equal to 2.
4的离散对数是2，因为2的平方是4
The discrete logarithm of 4 is 2, because 2 squared is equal to 4.
8的离散对数是3，因为2的立方是8
The discrete logarithm of 8 is 3, because 2 cubed is equal to 8.
等等。。那么这里我为大家写下了这些离散对数值
And so on and so forth. So here I wrote down the discrete logarithm values for you,
我问大家一个谜题：5模11的离散对数是什么？
and let me ask you a puzzle: what's the discrete logarithm of 5 modulo 11?
看看你是否可以自己算出来
See if you can calculate it yourself.
那么答案是4，因为2的4次方是16，即5模11
And so the answer is 4, because 2 to the 4 is equal to 16, and 16 is equal to 5 modulo 11.
好，这就是说，以2为底，5的离散对数是4
OK, so this says that the discrete logarithm base 2 of 5 is this number 4.
现在我可以告诉大家，一般情况下的离散对数函数的
计算是很困难的
Now I can tell you that the discrete logarithm function in general is actually quite difficult to compute.
当然，对于小质数而言是很容易的，可以做一张表
Of course for small primes, it's quite easy. You can just make a table
你可以读到离散对数值。但是如果质数p是个大数
and you can read off the discrete log values. But if the prime p happens to be a large number,
比如说有2000位，那么事实上计算离散对数是很困难的
say a 2000-bit number, then in fact computing the discrete log is quite difficult
我们没有好的算法来计算它
and we don't have good algorithms to do it.
那么我们更一般地定义离散对数问题
So let's define the discrete log problem more generically.
不再局限于群Z_p^*，我们更为抽象地看一个普通群G
Instead of just focusing on the group (Zp)*, let's abstract and look at a generic group G
那么我们有一个有限循环群，生成元是g
So we have a finite cyclic group with the generator g.
这意味着，这个群由g的各次幂组成
All that means is that this group just consists of all the powers of g.
我们取所有的幂，一共有阶数个，这里G的阶正好是q
So we take all the powers up to the order, in this case the order of G happens to be q,
那么我们取g的所有幂，这些幂组成了群G
so we take all the powers of g, and those powers actually make up the group capital-G.
现在我们说，群G上的离散对数问题是困难的
Now we're going to say that the discrete log problem is hard in the group G
如果事实上没有有效算法能够计算离散对数函数
if in fact no efficient algorithm can compute the discrete log function.
什么意思？意思是，如果你从群G中随机选择一个元素g
So what do we mean by that? What we mean is if you choose a random element g
你再随机选择一个指数x
in the group capital-G, and you choose a random exponent x,
如果我这个算法g和g^x，当然我还必须给它这个群的描述
if I give the algorithm g and g to the x―of course I also have to give it a description of the group,
那么我给它这个群G的描述，以及这个群的阶数
so I gave it the description of the group G, and the order of the group,
但最初的元素只有g和g^x
but the primary elements are g and g to the x―
这个算法会计算出离散对数的概率是可忽略的
the probability that the algorithm will actually compute the discrete log is negligible.
好，那么如果这点对所有的有效算法都成立
Ok, so if this is true for all efficient algorithms,
那么我们说在群G上，离散对数问题是困难的
then we say that the discrete log problem is hard in this group capital-G.
我们这样说的原因是因为没有有效算法
And again, the reason we say that is because no efficient algorithm is able
能够以不可忽略的概率计算出离散对数
to compute discrete log with non-negligible probability.
那么如我所说，我们有一组可选例子
So as I mentioned, we have a couple of candidate examples
其群上的离散对数是困难的
for groups where discrete log is hard.
经典的例子是Z_p^*，这个例子由Diffie和Hellman
The canonical example is (Zp)*, this is actually the example that Diffie and Hellman
于1974年发现，但实际上还有其他可选群
came up with in 1974, but it turns out there are other candidate groups
其离散对数问题是困难的，我想我提到过
where the discrete log problem happens to be hard, and I think I already mentioned
一个可选的是叫做椭圆曲线群
that one candidate is what's called the elliptic curve group,
(注意，实用的是离散的椭圆曲线)
或说，一条椭圆曲线上的点集。我这里不给出定义
or rather, the set of points on an elliptic curve. I'm not going to define that here,
但如我所说，如果大家想让我讨论椭圆曲线加密
but as I said, if you'd like me to talk about elliptic curve cryptography, I can do that actually
我可以在本课程的最后一周讲
in the very last week of the class.
(应该在第二季了，敬请期待)
这是两个群，上面的离散对数问题被认为是困难的
So these are two groups where the discrete log problem is in fact believed to be hard,
但我们目前知道，椭圆曲线上的离散对数问题
but it so happens that the discrete log problem actually is harder, as far as we know,
比Z_p^*上的离散对数问题要困难。
换句话说，如果给我等规模的问题
on elliptic curves than it is on (Zp)*. In other words, if you give me equal-sized problems
一个在群Z_p^*上，另一个在椭圆曲线群上
one set in the group (Zp)*, and one set in an elliptic curve group,
在椭圆曲线群上的问题要比Z_p^*上的困难得多
the problem set in the elliptic curve group is going to be much harder
假设两个问题的规模一样
than the problem in (Zp)*, again assuming these two problems are of the same size.
因为椭圆曲线群上的离散对数问题比Z_p^*上的困难得多
And because the elliptic curve problem, the discrete log elliptic curve problem is harder than in (Zp)*,
这意味着在椭圆曲线群上，我们可以使用更小的参数
this means that we can use smaller parameters when using elliptic curves
比起Z_p^*。因此，得到的椭圆曲线上的系统
than we can for (Zp)*, and as a result, the resulting systems with elliptic curves
要更加有效，因为参数更小
are going to be more efficient, because the parameters are smaller,
攻击者的难度与一个Z_p^*上的更大的质数相当
and yet the attacker's job is as hard as for a much larger prime in (Zp)*
(离散椭圆曲线的参数中也有一个大质数)
讲得更具体些，我告诉大家在Z_p^*中
So to make that concrete, I'll tell you that in (Zp)*, there's what's called
计算离散对数有一个亚指数算法，我想我提过这点
a sub-exponential algorithm for discrete log. So I think I already mentioned this,
如果你有一个n位的质数，这个算法的运行时间的指数
大约是n的立方根
if you have an n-bit prime, this algorithm will run in roughly cube root of n time.
事实上，在这个算法的运行时间里，这里有很多其他项
In fact there are many other terms in the exact running time of this algorithm,
但最主要的项是质数的位数的立方根
but the dominant term is cube root of the number of bits in the prime,
即n的立方根。因为有这个算法
so cube root of n. And because of this algorithm, you see that
如果我们想让离散对数问题变难
if we want the discrete log problem to be hard,
变得与破解相应的对称密钥一样难
as hard as it is to break a corresponding symmetric key,
我们必须使用较大的模p
we have to use relatively large moduli p.
相反，如果你看椭圆曲线群，参数会好很多
Now in contrast, if you look at an elliptic curve group, the numbers look much better,
事实上在一个椭圆曲线群里，我们对离散对数的最好算法
and in fact on an elliptic curve group, the best algorithm for discrete log that we have
运行时间为e的n/2次方。那么这是我们所说的
runs in time e to the n over 2. So this is what we would call
一个合适的指数时间算法，因为对于一个规模为n的问题
a proper exponential-time algorithm, because for a problem of size n,
其运行时间大约是e的n次方，为n次指数，
而不是n的立方根的指数
the running time is roughly e to the n. It's an exponential in n, not an exponential in cube root of n.
因为这个问题更加困难，我们有的最好的算法
And because the problem is so much harder, again the best algorithm we have
也要指数时间，大家注意到在椭圆曲线上
actually takes exponential time, you notice that in elliptic curves we can use
我们可以使用更小的参数，依然能保证安全
much smaller parameters and still remain secure.
顺便一说，椭圆曲线大小是对称密钥大小两倍的原因是
By the way, the reason the elliptic curve size is exactly twice the symmetric key size
(这里椭圆曲线大小指的是其质数模的大小)
由于指数里的这个因子2
is exactly because of this factor of 2 in the exponent here.
那么我们必须将椭圆曲线群的大小扩大一倍，
以获得e^n的运行时间
So we have to double the size of the elliptic curve for the problem to actually take e to the n time.
实际上我这里写错了，应该是2的n/2次方
And actually I made a small typo here in that this is actually supposed to be 2 to the n/2.
但对数的底并不重要
But the exact base of the logarithm doesn't really matter.
我想我之前提过，因为椭圆曲线的参数比Z_p^*更小
So I think I mentioned before that because the parameters are smaller with elliptic curves
从模p的密码转到椭圆曲线上的密码
than they are with (Zp)*, there's a slow transition from doing crypto modulo p
是缓慢的过程
to doing crypto over elliptic curves.
我再说一遍，如果大家希望我讲椭圆曲线的更多细节
And again I'll mention that if you want me to describe elliptic curves in more detail,
我可以留到本课程的最后一周
I can do that at the last week of the class.
现在我们理解了什么是离散对数问题
So now that we understand what the discrete log problem is,
我给大家一个离散对数困难性的直接应用
let me give you a direct application of the hardness of discrete log.
特别地，我们构建一个抗碰撞哈希函数，基于离散对数问题
An in particular, let's build a collision-resistant hash function from the discrete log problem.
我们选择一个群G，G上的离散对数问题是困难的
So let's choose some group capital-G where the discrete log problem is hard.
大家可以把G想象成群Z_p^*
So if you like, you can think of capital G as the group (Zp)*, and let's assume
我们假设群G有质数阶q，那么q是某个质数且正好为|G|
that the group capital G has prime order q. So q is some prime number that happens to be the order of G,
即群G里元素的个数
the number of elements in the group capital G.
现在定义我们的哈希函数，我们选择群G中的两个元素
Now to define our hash function, what we'll do is we'll choose two elements in the group capital G,
我们分别叫它们g和h，然后我们如下定义哈希函数：
and let's call them g and h, and then we'll define the hash function as follows:
哈希函数的输入为x和y时，输出g^x乘h^y
The hash function on input x and y will output an element in G defined as g to the x times h to the y.
完事了。好，一个非常简单的哈希函数。如果大家记得，
当我们以前讨论压缩函数的时候
That's it. Ok. A very very simple hash function, and if you recall, we even talked about this hash function
我们就讨论过这个哈希函数
when we talked about compression functions before.
我想给大家看，这个函数H事实上是抗碰撞的
I want to show you that this function capital-H is in fact collision-resistant
就是说，找到一个H的碰撞，与计算G上的离散对数一样困难
in the sense that finding a collision for capital H is as hard as computing discrete log in the group capital G.
特别地，如果你可以找到一个H的碰撞
Ok. So in particular, if you can find a collision for capital H,
你就能计算g底h的离散对数
you can compute the discrete log of h base g.
因为我们说过离散对数在群G上是困难的
And since we said the discrete log in the group capital G is hard,
计算离散对数应当是困难的
computing the discrete log should be difficult, and therefore
所以找H的碰撞也将是困难的
finding collisions for capital H is going to be difficult.
好，我们看为什么是这样。这是个很可爱的证明
Ok. So let's see how we do this. It's actually a very cute proof. What we'll do is, We'll do the following.
假设我们有一个函数H的碰撞
Suppose we are given a collision on the function capital H.
碰撞为两对不同的信息对，(x0,y0)与(x1,y1)，
它们正好在函数H上发生碰撞
So we're given two distinct pairs, (x0, y0) and (x1, y1), that happen to collide on the function capital H.
在函数H上碰撞是什么意思？
What does it mean that they collide on the function capital H? What it means is that
如果我计算函数值H(x0,y0)和H(x1,y1)，
我就会得到一个碰撞
if I evaluate the function capital H at (x0, y0) and (x1, y1), I'll get a collision.
也就是我会得到相等的结果。现在我可以来一些人为操作
Namely I'll get an equality. Well, so now I can just do a little bit of manipulation,
大家看到这意味着，我刚才把所有的g移到一边
and you see that this means I just move all the g's to one side
所有的h移到另一边，这意味着
and all the h's to the other side, so this means that
g^(x0-x1)=h^(y1-y0)，这一步是简单的
g to the (x0 - x1) is equal to h to the (y1 - y0), this is just simple manipulation.
现在我可以计算两边的1/(y1-y0)次方，换句话说
Now I can raise both sides to the power of 1/(y1 - y0). In other words I am taking the (y1 - y0)th root
我取两边的(y1-y0)次方根。那么一边会得到h
of both sides. So one side will become simply h,
另一边会变成g的(x0-x1)/(y1-y0)次方
and the other side will become g to the power of this fraction, (x0 - x1) divided by (y1 - y0).
现在看我们刚刚得到的。我们用g的某个幂表示了h
But now look at what we just got. Basically we expressed h as g to some known power.
我们只是除了一下，然后就突然证毕了
Basically all we did is just division, and boom, we're done. We've just expressed h
我们刚刚用g的某个幂表示了h，所以我们就计算出了
g底h的离散对数
as g to some known power. So we've computed the discrete log of h, base g.
那么大家会有疑问，这个指数的除法是什么意思？
So you might be wondering, what does this division in the exponent mean?
指数里除以(y1-y0)是什么意思？
What does it mean to divide by (y1 - y0) in the exponent?
这个意思就是让我们计算y1-y0的模q的逆
Well what it means is basically we compute the inverse of y1 - y0 modulo q,
然后把结果与x0-x1相乘，这会给我们明确的指数
and then we multiply the result by x0 - x1. And that gives us the exponent in the clear,
也就是我们解出的g底h的离散对数
and so we've just learned the discrete log of h base g.
这也为大家展示了，为什么我们希望q是指数。
因为我们需要确保y1-y0始终可逆
So this also shows you why we wanted q to be prime: because we need to make sure that y1 - y0
那么事实上我们知道，当我工作在质数模时
is always invertible. So in fact we know that when we work modulo prime,
除了0，所有数都可逆
everything is invertible except for zero.
这就遇到了一个难以理解的地方，如果y1-y0会怎样？
So that actually raises a subtle point, what happens if y1 - y0 actually happens to be equal to zero?
如果是这种情况，我们无法得到离散对数
If that's the case, then we are not going to be able to get the discrete log, because
我们不能除以0
we won't be able to divide by zero.
但如果大家想一想，你会发现
But if you think about this for a minute, you realize, well, let's see here.
如果y1-y0等于0，这意味着y1=y0
If y1 - y0 equals 0, that means that y1 is equal to y0.
但如果y1=y0，看这里的等式，这意味着
But if y1 is equal to y0, just look at this equation here, that means that
x0也必须等于x1
well, that necessarily means that x0 is also equal to x1.
大家很快就能说服自己，如果y0=y1
This takes you a minute to convince yourself, if y0 is equal to y1,
这两项相消，然后我们得到x0=x1
basically these two terms simply cancel out, and then we get that x0 is equal to x1.
但如果x0=x1且y0=y1，那么与碰撞的前提矛盾
But then if x0 is equal to x1, and y0 is equal to y1, what you gave me is not a collision.
相当于给了我同样的信息对两次。那么这是作弊，不算碰撞
You simply gave me the same pair twice. So that's cheating, so that's not considered a collision,
因此，我不需要去找离散对数了。但如果你给我一个碰撞
and therefore, you know, I don't need to find a discrete log. But if you give me a collision,
y0与y1有必要是不同的，然后
necessarily y0 is not going to be equal to y1, and then as a result
我将去计算h底g的离散对数
I'm going to get the discrete log of g base h.
如我们所说过的，由于群G上的离散对数被认为是困难的
And as we said, since the discrete log is believed to be hard in the group capital G,
这意味着这个非常简单的函数H一定是抗碰撞的
this means that this very very simple function capital H must be collision resistant.
这是一个非常优雅的例子，由找碰撞来计算离散对数
So this is a very elegant example of a reduction from finding collisions to computing discrete log.
我应该顺便告诉大家，这个函数不怎么用
I should tell you by the way that this function is not really used.
尽管这个函数有一个漂亮的抗碰撞的证明
Even though this function has a nice proof of collision resistance,
但它不怎么用，因为相对较慢
it's not really used because it's relatively slow. Essentially, on every hash
每次哈希你需要计算两次指数，
那比类似SHA-256的哈希函数慢得多
you have to compute two exponentiations, and that's much much much slower than, say, functions like SHA-256
或是其他随意设计的抗碰撞的哈希函数
and other kind of ad hoc collision-resistant hash functions.
好，这是我想说的关于质数模的难解问题
OK. So that's what I wanted to say about intractable problems modulo primes.
现在我们看一些合数模的难题
Now let's look at some intractable problems modulo composites.
这里我们再看，比如说，1024位数，我们定义集合Z_(2)n
So here we're gonna say ahh, again let's look at, say, 1024-bit numbers, and let's define the set Z-sub-2 n.
表示所有的整数，正好是两个质数的乘积
This is going to be the set of all integers that happen to be a product of two primes
而这两个质数都是n位的
where those two primes are n-bit primes.
好，那么这里的2对应于，这个集合里的数
Ok. So the 2 here corresponds to the fact that the numbers in this set
都有两个质因子，这两个质因子差不多大小
basically have 2 prime factors, and those two prime factors are roughly the same size.
它们都是n位的质数
They're both n-bit primes.
那么这个集合里有两个经典的难题
So there are two classic intractable problems in this set.
第一个问题是，如果我选择Z(2)(n)中一个随机整数，如何分解它？
The first problem is if I choose a random integer in the set Z(2)(n), the problem is, factor it.
对于1024位的大数，这已是一个难题
And already this is quite a difficult problem for 1024 bits.
尽管它还没有被解出来，但很有可能这个数量级的数
And although it hasn't been done yet, it's very likely that numbers of this magnitude
将很快被因子分解，那么现在推荐的值是2048位的数
will be factored soon, and so the recommended value these days is actually to use 2048-bit numbers.
2048位我们还是无能为力的，我们还不能因子分解这些数
That's still beyond our reach, and those are numbers that we still cannot factor.
另一个合数模的难题的例子是，给你某个
Another example of an intractable problem modulo composites is if I give you some polynomial
非线性多项式，如果多项式次数大于1，我给你Z(2)(n)中的
that's nonlinear, if the degree is bigger than 1, and I give you some random composite
某个随机的合数，你的目标是找到这个方程的根
in the set Z(2)(n), your goal is to find a root of this polynomial,
找到这个多项式的根x
find an x that happens to be a root of this polynomial.
我们也不知道怎么做；当然如果次数等于1
And again, we don't know how to do that; of course if the degree is equal to 1,
那就是解线性方程，我们知道那是容易的
that just amounts to solving linear equations, and we already know that, that's easy.
但当次数变成非线性时，我们不知道怎么解这个模N的方程
But the minute the degree becomes nonlinear, we don't know how to solve this modulo N
在不因子分解模的情况下直接计算根
without actually first factoring the modulus, and then computing roots.
有一些系统，例如RSA，就是依赖于这种困难性
So there are some systems, for example RSA, that depend on the hardness
对于特定多项式和问题，我们下周再行讨论之
of this particular problem for specific polynomials, which we're going to see next week.
仅举一例，我应该提一下，取平方根
And just as an example, I should mention that for example taking square roots
或立方根，模为Z(2)(n)里的随机合数，本认为是困难的
or cube roots modulo a random composite in Z(2)(n) is believed to be difficult.
关于分解问题，有很多已知的内容
So there's actually quite a bit known about the factoring problem.
这是一个很古老的问题。古希腊人就对因子分解感兴趣
It's actually a very old problem. Already the Greeks were interested in factoring,
但高斯有句名言是关于
but Gauss actually has a wonderful, wonderful quote that talks about
因子分解和素性检测的
the problem of factoring and the problem of primality testing.
在他的1905年的著名毕业论文里，他写道
So in his famous dissertation from 1805, he writes:
区分质数与合数的问题
"The problem of distinguishing prime numbers from composite numbers"
即所谓的素性检测
(this is what's called primality testing)
以及分解后者(合数)的问题
"and the problem of resolving the latter" (namely composites)
如何分解成质因子，是算术领域中最重要最有用的问题
"into their prime factors is known to be one of the most important and useful in arithmetic."
他对这些极为有趣的问题早有远见
So he had the foresight to realize that these are extremely interesting problems.
这些是计算机科学的问题。我们如何测试一个数是否为质数？
These are computer science problems essentially. How do we test if a number is prime?
我们如何分解一个不是质数是合数的数？
How do we factor a number if it's not a prime, if it's a composite?
高斯已经发现了，这些是极为重要和有趣的问题
And already Gauss realized that these are extremely extremely important and interesting problems,
如今，这些问题在网络上到处都在用
and now, these days, these problems are actually used on the Web all over the place.
我们看，事实上，测试一个数是否是质数的问题已经解决
So let's see. So, in fact, testing if a number is prime has been completely solved;
我们完全知道怎么办，即用一个随机算法
we now know completely how to do it, using, efficiently using a randomized algorithm,
我们甚至知道如何使用一个确定的算法
and we even know how to do it using a deterministic algorithm.
但分解数，把合数分解成质因数
Factoring numbers, factoring composites into their prime factors,
依然被认为是一个困难的问题。我鼓励大家去思考它
is still believed to be a difficult problem. I would encourage you actually to think about it.
这是一个极好的需思考的问题。如果你能解决它
It's a wonderful problem to think about. If any of you can solve it,
如果大家中的任何人能提出一个算法，来因子分解合数
if any of you can come up with an algorithm to factor composites into prime factors,
如我所说，你会在密码学界一战成名
again, as I said, it's instant fame in the crypto world, and it would have tremendous impact
而且对网络安全具有重大影响。那么这是一个有趣的问题去思考
on security of the Web in general. So it's a fun problem to think about.
我告诉大家，关于这个问题哪些是已知的
Let me tell you what's known about the problem of factoring.
目前最好的算法叫做数域筛法
So the best algorithm that we have is called the number field sieve.
它的运行时间是指数级，但是指数是立方根次的
Again, its running time is one of these exponentials, but a cube root of an exponential,
这也就是为什么合数要非常大，问题才会很难
which is why the composite has to be quite large for the problem to be difficult.
尽管目前的世界纪录是分解一个768位数
Although the current world record is really just factoring a 768-bit number.
这叫做RSA-768数，是一个挑战数，最近刚被分解
This is called the RSA-768 number, it's a challenge number that was recently factored.
这个数约10的200次方，分解这个数已然花掉大量的工作
The number is about 200 digits, and already factoring this number took an enormous amount of work.
历时两年，动用数百台机器，最后得以分解这个数
It took about two years on hundreds of machines, and finally they were able to factor this number.
估计分解1024位数，比分解RSA-768
And the estimate is that actually factoring a 1024-bit number is about 1000 times harder
难上近千倍，所以不是两年，可能要花两千年
than factoring RSA-768, so instead of 2 years, it would take two thousand years
不过当然计算机越来越快，处理器的核会更多
but of course computers are getting faster, we have more cores at our disposal,
我们有更多的计算机，假设摩尔定律成立
we have more computers, and so this factor of 1000, assuming Moore's Law and so on,
1000位数的分解只需花十年左右，计算机每十年
really just means a decade―you know, computers get faster by about a factor of
快一千倍，所以很有可能在下个年代里
1000 every decade, so it's very likely that within the next decade,
我们会看到1024位数的因子分解，宣告1024位
we'll see a factorization of a 1024-bit number, which would be the end of 1024 bits
在公钥密码中使用的终结
being used for public-key cryptography.
这是目前大数分解的现状。本章完结
So that's the state of the art in the factoring world, and this concludes this module.
如果大家想阅读本章中我们讨论过的话题的更多内容
I'll mention that if you want to read more about any of the topics that we discussed,
网上有一本很好的书，可免费下载的
there is a good book on the Internet, it's a free book that you can download,
由Victor Shoup所写的，特别地，我们讨论的内容
written by Victor Shoup, and in particular, the topics that we discussed
在这本书的第1、4、11、12章
are covered in chapters 1 to 4, 11, and 12.
我鼓励大家去看看
So I would encourage you to take a look at that, and hopefully that will help
希望对理解这些内容会有帮助
with understanding the material.
下周我们开始构建密码系统，使用我们学到的知识
Next week, we'll start building cryptosystems using the topics we just learned about.